In the last video, we gave
前回のビデオでは
a mathematical definition of how
ニューラルネットワークで使われる仮説を
to represent or how to
どう表現するか、または
compute the hypotheses used by Neural Network.
どう計算するかの数学的な定義を与えた。
In this video, I like
このビデオでは、
show you how to actually
その計算をどう実際に
carry out that computation efficiently, and
効率良く実行するかをお見せしたい、
that is show you a vector rise implementation.
これはベクトル化した実装を見せるという事。
And second, and more importantly, I want
次に、より重要な事として
to start giving you intuition about
これらのニューラルネットワークの表現が
why these neural network representations
なんで良さげなアイデアなのかを
might be a good idea and how
直感的に分かるような感覚を伝えたい。
they can help us to learn complex nonlinear hypotheses.
それらが非線形の複雑な仮説を学ぶ助けとなる。
Consider this neural network.
こんなニューラルネットワークを考えよう。
Previously we said that
以前、仮説の出力を得るのに
the sequence of steps that we
必要な計算の
need in order to compute
ステップは
the output of a hypotheses
これらの左にある
is these equations given on
式だと言った、
the left where we compute
アクティベーションの値があり
the activation values of the
3つの隠れユニットがあり
three hidden uses and then
それらを使って最終的な
we use those to compute the
仮説の出力、h(x)を
final output of our hypotheses
計算する。
h of x. Now, I'm going
ここで幾つか
to define a few extra terms.
追加の項を定義する。
So, this term that I'm
ここの下線を引いた
underlining here, I'm going to
この項は
define that to be
zの上付き添字2下付き添字1と
z superscript 2 subscript 1.
定義する。
So that we have that
つまりaの(2) 1は
a(2)1, which is this
つまりこの項は
term is equal to
gのz(2) 1と
g of z to 1.
等しくなる。
And by the
ところで
way, these superscript 2, you
これらの上付き添字2は
know, what that means is that
見ての通り、その意味は
the z2 and this a2
このz(2)とa(2)はともに
as well, the superscript
この上付きのカッコでくくられた2は
2 in parentheses means that these
これらの値が
are values associated with layer
2番目のレイヤーと関連づけられている事を意味する、
2, that is with the hidden
それはこの場合はニューラルネットワークの
layer in the neural network.
隠れレイヤに相当する。
Now this term here
同様にこの項を
I'm going to similarly define as
z(2)　2と
z(2)2.
定義する。
And finally, this last
最後に、この最後の
term here that I'm underlining,
下線を引いたこの項は、
let me define that as z(2)3.
z(2) 3と定義する。
So that similarly we have a(2)3
すると同様にa(2) 3は
equals g of
イコール
z(2)3.
gの z(2) 3となる。
So these z values are just
これらzの値は単なる
a linear combination, a weighted
個々のニューロンに入っていく
linear combination, of the
入力の値であるx0、
input values x0, x1,
x1、x2、x3の
x2, x3 that go into a particular neuron.
重み付けした線形和に過ぎない。
Now if you look at
ここでここ数のかたまりを
this block of numbers,
見てみると
you may notice that that block
この数のかたまりは
of numbers corresponds suspiciously similar
行列とベクトルの積に
to the matrix vector
どうも似ている。
operation, matrix vector multiplication
行列掛けるベクトルの
of x1 times the
シータ1 掛ける xに。
vector x. Using this observation
この観察に基づき、
we're going to be able to vectorize this computation
このニューラルネットワークの計算を
of the neural network.
ベクトル化出来る。
Concretely, let's define the
具体的に言うと、フィーチャーベクトルxを
feature vector x as usual
いつも通り、
to be the vector of x0, x1,
x0、x1、x2、x3のベクトルとしよう。ここで
x2, x3 where x0
x0はいつも通り
as usual is always equal
いつでも1とする。
1 and that defines
そしてz2ベクトルを
z2 to be the vector
これらのzの値、
of these z-values, you know, of z(2)1 z(2)2, z(2)3.
z(2) 1、z(2) 2、z(2) 3のベクトルと定義する。
And notice that, there, z2 this
そしてこの三次元ベクトル、
is a three dimensional vector.
z2を用いて、
We can now vectorize the computation
a(2) 1、 a(2) 2、 a(2) 3の計算を
of a(2)1, a(2)2, a(2)3 as follows.
以下のようにベクトル化する事が出来る。
We can just write this in two steps.
これを2つのステップで書く。
We can compute z2 as theta
z2は、シータ1掛けるxで
1 times x and that
計算出来る。
would give us this vector z2;
そしてそれでz2ベクトルが得られる。
and then a2 is
次にa2は
g of z2 and just
gのz2で計算出来る、
to be clear z2 here, This
ここではっきりさせておきたいのは、
is a three-dimensional vector and
このz2は三次元ベクトルで
a2 is also a three-dimensional
a2も三次元ベクトルという事。
vector and thus this
だからこのactivation g、
activation g. This applies the
これはz2の各要素に対し
sigmoid function element-wise to each
sigmoid関数を
of the z2's elements. And
適用した物。
by the way, to make our notation
ところで、のちほどのノーテーションと
a little more consistent with
もう少し一貫させておくと
what we'll do later, in this
この入力レイヤーは
input layer we have the
入力がxな訳だが
inputs x, but we
それは最初のレイヤの
can also thing it is
アクティベーションとも
as in activations of the first layers.
考えられる。
So, if I defined a1 to
だからa1をxと
be equal to x. So,
定義する。
the a1 is vector, I can
つまりa1はベクトルで
now take this x here
ここのxを
and replace this with z2 equals theta1
置き換えて、z2イコール
times a1 just by defining
シータ1掛けるa1となる、
a1 to be activations in my input layer.
a1を入力レイヤのアクティベーションとしただけ。
Now, with what I've written
さて、ここまで書いてきた事で
so far I've now gotten
いまやa1、a2、a3の値を
myself the values for a1,
得た訳だが
a2, a3, and really
ここでも
I should put the
上付き添字を
superscripts there as well.
つけておこう。
But I need one more
だがもう一つ必要な値がある、
value, which is I also want this a(0)2
それはa(0) 2だ、
and that corresponds to
それはつまり
a bias unit in the
隠れレイヤの
hidden layer that goes to the output there.
バイアスユニットで、それは出力のここに行く。
Of course, there was a
もちろん、ここにも
bias unit here too that,
バイアスユニットはある。
you know, it just didn't draw
ここの下には
under here but to
書かなかっただけで。
take care of this extra bias unit,
だがこの追加のバイアスユニットを扱う為に
what we're going to do is add
ここに追加の
an extra a0 superscript 2,
a(0) 2を足す。
that's equal to one, and after
それはイコール1だ。
taking this step we now have
このステップを経る事で
that a2 is going to
a2を4次元のフィーチャーベクトルとして
be a four dimensional feature
得る事が出来た。
vector because we just added
何故ならたった今この
this extra, you know,
追加のa0を
a0 which is equal to
それはイコール1で
1 corresponding to the bias unit
隠れレイヤーのバイアスユニットに対応するが
in the hidden layer. And finally,
それを足したからだ。 そして最後に
to compute the actual
実際に仮説の出力を
value output of our hypotheses, we
計算するために、
then simply need to compute
z3を計算する必要がある。
z3. So z3 is
z3はここの下線を引いた所に
equal to this term here that I'm just underlining.
この項に等しい。
This inner term there is z3.
この内側の項がz3だ。
And z3 is stated
そしてz3はシータ2掛ける
2 times a2 and finally
a2だ。
my hypotheses output h of x which
そして最終的に、仮説の出力であるhのxは、
is a3 that is
a3で、
the activation of my
それは出力レイヤの
one and only unit in
唯一のアクティベーションだ。
the output layer. So, that's just the real number. You can write it as a3
つまり単なる実数で、a3は
or as a(3)1 and that's g of z3.
a(3) 1とも書けるが、それはgのz3だ。
This process of computing h of x
このhのxを計算するプロセスは
is also called forward propagation
フォワードプロパゲーションとも呼ばれる。
and is called that because we
その訳は入力ユニットの
start of with the activations
アクティベーションから始めて
of the input-units and then
そしてある意味で
we sort of forward-propagate that to the
隠れレイヤに対し、
hidden layer and compute the activations of the
前方(フォワード)に伝播(プロパゲート)させて
hidden layer and then we
アクティベーションを計算し、
sort of forward propagate that
それをさらに前方へ伝播させていって
and compute the activations of
出力レイヤのアクティベーションを
the output layer, but this process of computing the activations from the input then
計算するからだ。入力から始めて
the hidden then the output layer,
隠れレイヤ、そして出力レイヤ。
and that's also called forward propagation
それをフォワードプロパゲーションと呼ぶ。
and what we just did is
そしてここまでやったのは
we just worked out a vector
この手順の
wise implementation of this
ベクトル化した実装を遂げたという事。
procedure. So, if you
だからこの右側にある
implement it using these equations
式でそれを実装すれば
that we have on the right, these
hのxを計算する
would give you an efficient way
効率的な方法と
or both of the efficient way of
なってくれると
computing h of x.
言う訳だ。
This forward propagation view also
このフォワードプロパゲーションの見方は
helps us to understand what
ニューラルネットワークが何を
Neural Networks might be doing
してくれるかを理解する助けともなってくれ、
and why they might help us to
それは何故ニューラルネットワークが興味深い非線形の仮説を
learn interesting nonlinear hypotheses.
学習する助けとなるかもしれないかも教えてくれる。
Consider the following neural network
以下のようなニューラルネットワークを考えてみよう、
and let's say I cover up
そしてこの図の左側の部分を
the left path of this picture for now.
カバーで隠すとしよう。
If you look at what's left in this picture.
この図の残った所を見ると、
This looks a lot like
これはまるで
logistic regression where what
ロジスティック回帰のようだ、
we're doing is we're using
我らがやってる事は
that note, that's just the
このノードを使って、
logistic regression unit and we're
このノードは単なるロジスティック回帰だ、
using that to make a
それを使ってhのxという
prediction h of x. And concretely,
予言を行う。 具体的には
what the hypotheses is outputting
仮説が出力するのは
is h of x is going
hのxは
to be equal to g which
イコール、gの、、、
is my sigmoid activation function times theta 0
これはsigmoid関数のアクティベーションだが、それに
times a0 is equal
シータ0掛けるa0足すことの
to 1 plus theta 1
シータ1掛けるa1
plus theta 2
足すことのシータ2掛けるa2
times a2 plus theta
足すことのシータ3掛けるa3で、
3 times a3 whether
ここで値
values a1, a2, a3
a1、a2、a3は
are those given by these three given units.
これらのユニットから得られる値。
Now, to be actually consistent
これまでのノーテーションと
to my early notation. Actually, we
一貫させる為には
need to, you know, fill in
ここの全部に
these superscript 2's here everywhere
上付き添字の2 を追加する必要がある。
and I also have these
さらにこれらの
indices 1 there because I
ここの所に1を追加する必要がある、何故なら
have only one output unit, but if you focus on the blue parts of the notation.
出力ユニットは一つしか無いから。 でもこの青い部分に集中して見ると、
This is, you know, this looks
これはいかにも普通の
awfully like the standard logistic
ロジスティック回帰のモデルで、
regression model, except that
小文字のシータの代わりに
I now have a capital theta instead of lower case theta.
大文字のシータって所だけが違う。
And what this is
そしてこれがやってる事は
doing is just logistic regression.
単なるロジスティック回帰だ。
But where the features fed into
だがロジスティック回帰に食わせる
logistic regression are these
フィーチャーは、隠れレイヤによって
values computed by the hidden layer.
計算されるこれらの値だ。
Just to say that again, what
もう一度言おう。
this neural network is doing is
このニューラルネットワークがやる事は
just like logistic regression, except
ロジスティック回帰みたいなもんだが、
that rather than using the
もともとのフィーチャーである
original features x1, x2, x3,
x1、x2、x3を使う代わりに
is using these new features a1, a2, a3.
これらの新しいフィーチャーa1、a2、a3を使うって所だけが違う。
Again, we'll put the superscripts
ここでも上付き添字をつけた、
there, you know, to be consistent with the notation.
ノーテーションを揃える為だ。
And the cool thing about this,
これのクールな所は
is that the features a1, a2,
フィーチャーa1，a2，a3，は
a3, they themselves are learned
それら自身が入力の関数として
as functions of the input.
学習された物である、という事。
Concretely, the function mapping from
具体的には、レイヤー1からレイヤー2へと
layer 1 to layer 2,
マッピングする関数、
that is determined by some
それは別のパラメータの組である
other set of parameters, theta 1.
シータ1で定義される。
So it's as if the
つまりニューラルネットワークは
neural network, instead of being
ロジスティック回帰への
constrained to feed the
入力のフィーチャーを
features x1, x2, x3 to logistic regression.
x1、x2、x3、に制限する代わりに
It gets to
独自のフィーチャー
learn its own features, a1,
a1，a2，a3を学習して
a2, a3, to feed into the
それをロジスティック回帰に
logistic regression and as
食わせられるような物だ。
you can imagine depending on
そして想像出来ると思うが、
what parameters it chooses for
シータ1に何を選ぶかによって
theta 1. You can learn some pretty interesting
とても興味深く複雑な
and complex features and therefore
フィーチャーを学習出来て、
you can end up with a
それゆえに、結果として
better hypotheses than if
単に生のフィーチャーx1、x2、x3に
you were constrained to use
食わせるフィーチャーを限定したり、
the raw features x1, x2 or x3 or if
その多項式、
you will constrain to say choose the
x1x2、x2x3などの多項式から選ぶより
polynomial terms, you know,
より良い仮説が
x1, x2, x3, and so on.
得られる。
But instead, this algorithm has
このアルゴリズムはそれらの代わりに
the flexibility to try
どんなフィーチャーでも一旦
to learn whatever features at once, using
学習する柔軟性があり、
these a1, a2, a3 in
そしてこれらa1，a2，a3を使って
order to feed into this
この最後のユニットに食わせる為に使う事が出来、
last unit that's essentially
この最後は本質的には
a logistic regression here. I realized
ここのロジスティック回帰だ。
this example is described as
ここに記述された例は
a somewhat high level and so
いくらかハイレベルで、
I'm not sure if this intuition
このニューラルネットワークの直感的な話が
of the neural network, you know, having
つまりより複雑なフィーチャーを
more complex features will quite
使うというのが
make sense yet, but if
ピンと来てるか怪しい、というのは分かってる。
it doesn't yet in the next
でもまだピンと来ないなぁ、と思ってても、
two videos I'm going to
次の2つのビデオで、
go through a specific example
ニューラルネットワークが
of how a neural network can
この隠れユニットを使って
use this hidden there to compute
より複雑なフィーチャーを計算して
more complex features to feed
それをこの最後のレイヤに食わせるか、という
into this final output layer
具体例を見ていく。
and how that can learn more complex hypotheses.
そしてどうやってより複雑な仮説を学ぶ事が出来るのかということも見ていく。
So, in case what I'm
だからもし今回のビデオで
saying here doesn't quite make
私が言った事がいまいちピンと来なくても
sense, stick with me
次の2つのビデオに
for the next two videos and
頑張ってついてきてくれれば、
hopefully out there working through
それらの例を通して、
those examples this explanation will
きっとこの説明が
make a little bit more sense.
よりはっきり分かると思う。
But just the point O. You
だけど指摘しておくと、
can have neural networks with
他の図式の形のニューラルネットワークも
other types of diagrams as
可能で、
well, and the way that
ニューラルネットワークがどう
neural networks are connected, that's called the architecture.
接続されるかはアーキテクチャと呼ばれる。
So the term architecture refers to
つまりアーキテクチャという用語は
how the different neurons are connected to each other.
異なるニューロンが互いにどう接続されるかを表す言葉。
This is an example
これは異なるニューラルネットの
of a different neural network architecture
アーキテクチャの例だ。
and once again you may
ここでもういちど
be able to get this intuition of
以下のような直感を得ることが出来るかもしれない、
how the second layer,
それは二番目のレイヤ、
here we have three heading units
ここの3つのユニットが
that are computing some complex
何か複雑な関数、
function maybe of the
入力レイヤの複雑な関数を
input layer, and then the
計算し、そして次に
third layer can take the
三番目のレイヤが二番目のレイヤから
second layer's features and compute
フィーチャーを受け取り、
even more complex features in layer three
さらに複雑なフィーチャーを三番目のレイヤで行い、
so that by the time you get
だから出力レイヤ、つまり四番目のレイヤに
to the output layer, layer four,
たどり着く頃には
you can have even more
レイヤ3で計算した
complex features of what
さらに複雑なフィーチャーを
you are able to compute in
使う事が出来て、
layer three and so get very interesting nonlinear hypotheses.
だからとても興味深い非線形の仮説を得る事が出来る、という事。
By the way, in a network
ところで、こんなネットワークでも
like this, layer one, this is
1つ目のレイヤ、これは
called an input layer. Layer four
入力レイヤと呼ばれ、
is still our output layer, and
レイヤ4も出力レイヤのままだ、
this network has two hidden layers.
そしてこのネットワークは2つの隠れレイヤを持っている。
So anything that's not an
つまり入力レイヤでもなく
input layer or an output
出力レイヤでも無い物は
layer is called a hidden layer.
全て隠れレイヤと呼ぶ。
So, hopefully from this video
さて、このビデオで、
you've gotten a sense of
ニューラルネットワークのフォワードプロパゲーションのステップが
how the feed forward propagation step
どういう感じで機能するか、
in a neural network works where you
分かっていただけただろうか。
start from the activations of
入力レイヤのアクティベーションから
the input layer and forward
始めて、前方に伝播させていき、
propagate that to the
まず最初の隠れレイヤ、次に
first hidden layer, then the second
二番目の隠れレイヤ、と、
hidden layer, and then finally the output layer.
そして最後に出力レイヤへと伝播させていく。
And you also saw how
そしてまた、それをどう
we can vectorize that computation.
ベクトル化して計算するかも見た。
In the next, I realized
次回にやる事は、
that some of the intuitions in this
こごでの直感的な話、
video of how, you know, other certain
このビデオでやったあるレイヤが
layers are computing complex features of the early layers.
前のレイヤの複雑なフィーチャーを計算する、という話が
I realized some of that intuition
いくらかそれらの直感的な話は、
may be still slightly abstract and kind of a high level.
まだちょっと抽象的で高級だと思う。
And so what I would like
だから次の2つの動画で私は
to do in the two videos
ニューラルネットワークが
is work through a detailed example
入力の非線形の関数として
of how a neural network can
複雑な計算が行えるかの
be used to compute nonlinear
具体例をより詳細に
functions of the input and
見ていきたい。
hope that will give you a
それを通して、ニューラルネットワークで出来る
good sense of the sorts of
複雑な非線形の仮説についての
complex nonlinear hypotheses we can get out of Neural Networks.
感覚が良く身に着くことを狙って。